Today's דף daf *daf* is דף *daf* מ *Mem*.
Is that correct? Yes—no, today's דף *daf* is דף מ"א Daf Mem
Aleph. *daf Mem Aleph*, and we pick up towards the bottom of
דף מ' עמוד ב' *daf Mem Amud Bet*. So we pick up
with—we had just discussed what is considered cooking by water, יד סולדת
בו yad soledes bo, *Yad Soledet Bo*, oil, different opinions, does it
cook earlier, later, same time? And we also said by oil, יד
סולדת בו yad soledes bo *Yad Soledet Bo*. And now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* picks up with אמר רב amar Rav, יצחק בר אבדימי
*Amar Rav Yitzchak Bar Avdimi*. It's one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven, about ten lines down in the wide lines. It starts with
the phrase של תינוק נכוה *shel tinok nichvei*. So let's take a
look. אמר רב amar Rav יצחק בר אבדימי *Amar Rav Yitzchak Bar
Avdimi*, so said רב Rav, יצחק בר אבדימי *Rav Yitzchak Bar Avdimi*,
פעם אחת נכנסתי
אחר רבי Rebbe's לבית המרחץ *Pa'am achat nichnasti achar Rebbe l'beit hamerchatz*.
One time I followed רבי *Rebbe* into the study hall—not study
hall—into the בית המדרש *Beis Hamedrash*, בית המרחץ beis hamerchatz? *Beis Hamerchatz*.
All right, I'm obviously a little bit פאַרטומלט *fartumelt* here. One time
I followed רבי *Rebbe* into the bathhouse, and
it was presumably שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. וביקשתי להניח לו פך של שמן
shemen באמבטי *U'vikashti lehaniach lo pach shel shemen ba'ambati*. And I wanted
to put a flask of oil in the bath, in the—because I,
you know, because I wanted to warm it up. It was שבת
Shabbos. *Shabbos*. Now of course the question is, what's רבי *Rebbe* doing
in the bathhouse? We just learned the other day you're not allowed
to be in a bathhouse on a fast—fully immerse your body in
hot water on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*. So רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says, and
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* itself is going to say in a minute,
that it was basically we'll have to assume it was חמי טבריא
*chamei Tverya*. It was like the wellsprings of Tiberias. It was heated
up from some non-fire source. Okay, and I wanted to put this
flask of oil into the bath to heat it up, to warm
it up.
It's already hot.
For him. It says להניח לו *lenaniach lo*. I
guess you're right. Yeah, for him. Okay, fine. Good point. ואמר לי
*V'amar li*, and he said to me, טול בכלי שני ותן *Tol
bikli sheni v'ten*. Take water in a second vessel and then put
the oil in the flask into that second vessel. Do
not—what do you call it?
Do
not—I'm sorry, do not go ahead and put it directly in the
bath. The bath is considered a כלי ראשון kli rishon *kli rishon*.
It's the vessel in which the water was initially heated up and
that, as we will find out later but also today's גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is a very serious source for that idea, that objects only
cook in a כלי ראשון kli rishon, *kli rishon*. So don't put
it in the bath itself. That bathtub is a כלי ראשון kli
rishon *kli rishon*. Take hot water from that in some type of
a pot and then put the flask of oil into that pot.
So the oil is in the water and the water is in
a כלי שני kli sheni *kli sheni*, is in the second vessel,
not the vessel it was heated up in, but in a second
vessel. And things are not considered to cook in a כלי שני
kli sheini? *kli sheni*. So question. Yes.
So we say that it was permissible for him to immerse because
he wasn't in a bathhouse per se, it was like hot springs.
So nobody had heated the water.
But then what's the problem with the oil?
But then he's not sitting in the כלי ראשון kli rishon *kli
rishon* because the water was hot already, it wasn't heated
in—so that's an excellent question too. So
if the water wasn't heated by a fire, then what's the problem
about putting the oil into that water also? Because it's not—right. So
in terms of the problem of the oil in the water, that
would be maybe a דרבנן d'rabonon, *d'rabbanan* because it's תולדות חמה toldot
chama, *toldos chama*. You know, so it's not directly in the sun,
it's second degree, so even though it wasn't heated by a fire,
there's still a דרבנן *d'rabbanan*.
But the simpler sense, but of course the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has
to assume otherwise, is that it is in a bath that was
heated by a fire, it is a real כלי ראשון kli rishon
*kli rishon*, and that was the problem putting the oil and sort
of bracketing the issue about how רבי *Rebbe* could be in a
מרחץ merchatz *merchatz*, but you can't say that because we've just laid
out the idea right that a מרחץ *merchatz*—that you can't be in
a מרחץ *merchatz* on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. So let's hold off for
that. I'll go back to your question. Let's first see where this
ends. So he says put it into a second vessel.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, שמע מינה shema
mina, תלת *Shema mina telat*, and we see from this three things.
שמע מינה שמן יש בו משום בישול shema mina shemen yesh bo
mishum bishul. *Shema mina shemen yesh bo mishum bishul*. He was concerned
about the oil cooking, so the discussion yesterday about whether it's considered
to be cooking with oil or not, so we see from this
that it is.
אוי ואבוי *Oy vavoy*.
Hold on a second. Just have to figure out something here that's
going to keep—I need more tape or something. I don't know. Ah,
I'm sorry. Yeah no,
we need more—bit more tape or something. All right anyway, שמן יש
בו משום בישול bishul, *shemen yesh bo mishum bishul*. That's pulling it?
Okay, now it's okay. It was pulling it.
Okay. Just crouch down a little that's all. What? Just crouch down.
Crouch down.
All right anyway
hold on I'm sorry everybody.
Try it like that. Still not doing any good. All right. Anyway
hold on I'm sorry. שמן יש בו משום בישול. bishul. So number
one it's possible to cook oil so here was a problem of
cooking the oil. ומשמע מינה Vushma mina כלי שני אינו מבשל. kli
sheni eino mevashel.
This is extremely key for later aspects of הלכה halacha that if
it's in a second vessel it's not considered cooking. ומשמע מינה הפשרה
זהו בישולו. Vushma mina hafshara zehu bishulo. Now what it also sounds
like is although in a second vessel presumably it would not get
super hot, it wouldn't get יד סולדת בו, yad soledes bo. but
just dissolving it is considered like cooking it which is not what
we said yesterday. Yesterday we said it had to get to the
stage of being
a יד סולדת בו yad soledet bo. and here it seems like
it's not such that that's not so much that it would be
considered a problem even with less than that.
So that in the end if that's what the גמרא Gemara means
then that's not exactly how we rule because we rule that even
by oil it has to get to יד סולדת בו. yad soledet
bo. Anyway the גמרא Gemara now says היכי עביד הכי? Heichi avid
hachi? How did he do this? דהא אמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן בכל מקום מותר להרהר חוץ מבית המרחץ. Deha amar
Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan bechol makom mutar leharher chutz
mibeis hamerchatz.
So the גמרא Gemara asks an interesting side question. Don't we say
that you're not allowed to think in a bathroom you're not allowed
to talk of תורה Torah in a בית המרחץ? beis hamerchatz God's
sakes okay you know what I cannot believe forget it
everything is working and we don't have this lousy thing working.
One other no let's get
I cannot believe hold
on I'll try this. All right okay fine all right fine move
on let's move on. Let's move on let's move on. Anyway okay
how could you say that? Don't we say that you're not allowed
to talk תורה Torah in a בית המרחץ ובית הכסא? ubeis hakisei?
So וכי תימא בלשון חול אמר ליה vichi teima belashon chol amar
lei
maybe he said it to him in not in Hebrew but in
some type of other but you know in some in the vernacular
and therefore maybe the problem is speaking about תורה Torah in Hebrew
maybe that gives it a different status. דאמר אביי ודאביי אמר דברים
של חול מותר לאמרם בלשון הקודש de'amar Abaye ved'Abaye amar devarim shel
chol mutar lomram belashon hakodesh
it's not the language you use it's the content. You can say
non תורה Torah things even in Hebrew ושל קודש אסור לאמרם בשל
חול veshel kodesh asur lomram beshel chol
and תורה Torah things you can't say even in the vernacular even
not in Hebrew. So it's not about what language you use it's
about what you are speaking. Now תוספות Tosafot by the way points
out that it says that the issue is whether you're even allowed
to think תורה Torah in a bathroom. So תוספות Tosafot says you're
not even saying the words he said okay but maybe it's still
a difference are you thinking תורה Torah in Hebrew? Are you thinking
תורה Torah in the vernacular? What language you're thinking in your head?
But anyway the גמרא Gemara says it in the end it doesn't
matter what language you're using it's the content of what you're speaking.
So how therefore was he able to say it? Now it's quite
interesting because you'll notice he didn't even say here's the הלכה. halacha.
He said use a different vessel. So he's not even really directly
talking about הלכה halacha implicitly a certain הלכתי halachic concerns but all
he's telling him is don't put it straight in the bathhouse take
it out in another vessel. So even that which is quite fascinating
the גמרא Gemara considers to be a type of speaking תורה. Torah.
So how is that allowed? So the גמרא Gemara says אפרושי מאיסורא
שאני. afrushei mei'isura shani. It's different if you're trying to stop somebody
from doing an עבירה. aveira. So therefore although you're not allowed to
talk תורה Torah in the bathhouse and the bathroom if you're trying
to stop them from doing an עבירה aveira then you could say
something and therefore he was able to say don't put it straight
in the bath.
But you can't do it as soon as some kind of עבירה
aveira like if you say it's like you know oh it's קריאת
שמע Krias Shema time or something like that.
Yeah it's an interesting question. No. So the גמרא Gemara says שאני
shani what?
How do I know since it was implicit how do we know
that he didn't want to put it straight in the bath because
he was afraid the cap would fall off and be lost?
Well I guess it was the technical use of כלי שני kli
sheini. which was more הלכתי halachic terminology it be actually it's become
הלכתי halachic terminology it's not so clear then if it was. But
yeah it is interesting he didn't straight talk תורה. Torah. Anyway let's
take a look דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל מעשה בתלמידו של רבי
מאיר שנכנס אחריו לבית המרחץ. de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel ma'aseh betalmido
shel Rabbi Meir shenichnas acharav leveis hamerchatz. There's a story about the
students of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that came after him into the
bathhouse וביקש להדיח קרקע uvikeish lehaduach karka and it was שבת Shabbos
presumably again interesting all these people going into the מרחץ on שבת.
Shabbos וביקש להדיח קרקע uvikeish lehaduach karka he wanted to wash the
floor ואמר לו אין מדיחין ve'amar lo ein medichin you can't wash
the floor. Why? Because there's a concern that you'll come to smooth
out the holes and that will and that will be an עבירה
aveira on שבת. Shabbos. לסוך לו קרקע lasuch lo karka he wanted
to therefore like put oil on the floor maybe also to make
it more pleasant for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir to walk there. אמר
לו אין סכין amar lo ein sachin you cannot put oil on
it. Again a problem that you'll come to smooth out the holes.
So you see he told תורה. Torah. Now again now this is
actually a little more תורה Torah because אין סכין ein sachin right?
אין מדיחין ein medichin is like a הלכתי halachic language you're not
allowed to. So even though it's so that at least the גמרא
Gemara considers to be talking תורה. Torah. אלמא אפרושי מאיסורא שאני alma
afrushei mei'isura shani so obviously what must have allowed it was he
was stopping him from doing an עבירה. aveira. הכא נמי כדי לאפרושי
מאיסורא שאני hacha nami kedei le'afrushei mei'isura shani it's allowed to separate
him from an עבירה. aveira. Right, אין מדיחים ein medichim is like
a halakhic language, you're not allowed to. So even though it's something
that at least the גמרא Gemara considers to be talking Torah, אלא
מאי ela mai להפריש מן האיסור שאני, lehafrish min ha'issur shani, so
obviously what must have allowed it was he was stopping him from
doing an עבירה. aveira. So הכא נמי hacha nami here too להפריש
מן האיסור שאני, lehafrish min ha'issur shani, it's allowed to separate him
from an עבירה. aveira. Okay, so that's in terms of why did
he say, why was he allowed to say it in a bathhouse.
But now we get back to the fundamental שבת Shabbos issue, which
is that he could not put the oil directly in the bath,
but he could take it out in a second כלי. kli. So,
says Ravina, שמע מינה, we hear from this, המבשל
בחמי טבריה בשבת חייב. hamvashil b'chamei Teverya b'Shabbos chayav. It sounds like
you transgress biblically שבת Shabbos if you do it in the hot
springs of טבריה, Teverya, which is exactly against everything we've been saying
until now, which is if it's not heated by a fire, it's
not a biblical transgression. Why does it sound like that? דהא מעשה
דרבי לאחר גזירה הוה. d'ha ma'aseh d'Rebbi l'achar gezeira havah. Rebbi's story
was after the גזירה, gezeira, after they don't allow you to be
in a bathhouse. So this is exactly the point. The simpler sense
would be that Rebbi was in a bathhouse with water heated by
a fire, and that's why the whole thing was a problem. But
he says no, the chronology doesn't work out. Rebbi came after the
earlier Tannaitic layer where we said that you don't go to a
bathhouse, you don't go to water heated by a fire on שבת
Shabbat. even if it was heated before שבת. Shabbat? So therefore the
Rebbi story had to only be חמי טבריה. Chamei Teverya. And once
that's the case, ואמר ליה טול בכלי שני ותני. v'amar lei tol
b'kli sheini u'tenei. Put it in a second vessel, you can't put
it straight in the bath. So therefore why is that a problem?
I mean,
it's only, it's not heated by a fire. So the גמרא Gemara
says, איני? ini? Can you really say that? ואמר רב חסדא המבשל
בחמי טבריה בשבת פטור. v'amar Rav Chisda hamvashil b'chamei Teverya b'Shabbos patur.
That if you cook in חמי טבריה Chamei Teverya on שבת Shabbat,
you're פטור. patur. So therefore it obviously cannot be. Now maybe again,
maybe the גמרא Gemara was debating because if you remember yesterday, there's
a question whether we consider חמי טבריה Chamei Teverya to be like
heated by a fire or to be in the category of heated
by the sun. How do חמי טבריה Chamei Teverya get hot? So
maybe that's part of what the גמרא's Gemara issue was. But since
we basically say חמי טבריה Chamei Teverya is not considered heated by
a fire, and that would be why Rebbi was allowed to be
in the bath, what would be the big deal about putting oil
in it? So maybe it would be a Rabbinic issue, but it
sounded like it was more of a biblical issue. So the גמרא
gemara says no, מאי חייב נמי דקאמר, mai chayav nami d'ka'amar, when
the גמרא gemara says we infer from it that if you put
in that you're חייב chayav if you were to put the oil
directly in, actually the גמרא gemara didn't use the word חייב chayav
before, it said שמע מינה שמן יש בו משום בישול. bishul But
anyway, when was there a sense there of transgression דקאמר מכת מרדות.
d'ka'amar makat mardut. It means a Rabbinic transgression, you would get lashes,
but it would not be biblical. So what the גמרא gemara said
now is the scenario of Rebbi, what was Rebbi doing in the
bathhouse? Must have been that it was חמי טבריה, Chamei Teverya, which
means that it's not considered cooking. So why was Rebbi getting so
worried and saying put it in a כלי שני? Kli Sheni. That's
because there would still be a Rabbinic restriction of cooking something in
חמי טבריה Chamei Teverya in תולדות חמה, toldos chamah but it would
not have been biblical. Okay, so that just frames it all as
Rabbinic because it was not directly heated by a fire. But in
terms of the bigger question, we hear some important principle here, which
is number one, okay, שמן can you can be חייב chayav for
cooking, which was yesterday's discussion, not exactly clear how hot, here it
says just liquefying it, yesterday it said יד סולדת בו. yad soledet
bo But the bigger issue is a distinction between כלי ראשון kli
rishon. and כלי שני. Kli Sheni Now Paula asks why is it
considered to be a כלי ראשון, kli rishon if this is coming
from חמי טבריה, Chamei Teverya, right, so it's not like it was
originally cooked in this vessel wherever the bath is. So if you
look at רש"י, Rashi רש"י Rashi says
let's see if רש"י Rashi says this. If רש"י Rashi has about
six lines before the lines get wide, he says the lines start
towards לתוך, letoch, maybe eight lines before they get wide. רש"י Rashi
says תן פכך לתוך אותו כלי שני דהכא באמבטי שהחמים נמשכין לה
מן המעיין חשיב ליה ככלי ראשון שנרתחו בו. ten pachach letoch oto
kli sheini d'hacha b'ambati shehachamim nimshachin lah min hamayan chashiv lei k'kli
rishon shenirtachu bo.
That this bath where the water is drawn from the wellsprings is
considered a כלי ראשון kli rishon, as if it was cooked in
this, why, אף על פי שהעבירו מעל האור מבשל af al pi
she'he'eviru me'al ha'ur mevashel because a כלי ראשון kli rishon? even if
it's not on the fire. So it's true this bath was not
directly over the fire, but a כלי ראשון kli rishon even when
you removed it from the fire is a כלי ראשון. kli rishon,
Now there's still a problem. But that's because a כלי ראשון Kli
Rishon initially was on a fire. This bathtub never was initially. But
what רש"י Rashi seems to be saying, and this is actually quite
important for us in the contemporary scenario is, let me ask you
a question, when you turn on your faucet in your house on
שבת Shabbat and it's drawing water straight from the hot water heater
and the water comes out, what's the status of that water? Is
that considered to be כלי ראשון, Kli Rishon. like עירוי כלי ראשון
irui kli rishon poured from a כלי ראשון? Kli Rishon I mean
the hot water heater is
way in the basement. But the point is is that some people
will say yes it is כלי ראשון Kli Rishon because the hot
water heater, it's one unit, the whole hot water with the attached
pipe, and it's all even though the pipe is not on the
fire, it's all part of the same unit that's on the fire
and the water anywhere in the pipe is a כלי ראשון, Kli
Rishon. maybe later in the pipe it's כלי ראשון שלא על גבי
האש, kli rishon shelo al gabei ha'esh, but it's all part of
the unit that was on the fire, and when it's poured out
it's considered to be עירוי כלי ראשון. irui kli rishon.
So that seems to be somewhat of what רש"י Rashi is saying,
that if you've got a bath and it's all connected of water
coming from the wellsprings of טבריה Teverya and emptying into the bath,
that maybe all of that seems to be considered to be like
one unit. That seems to be why רש"י's Rashi, understanding if once
we say it's not a problem if you didn't say it was
חמי טבריה, Chamei Teverya, but once you say it's חמי טבריה Chamei
Teverya why would... It's still considered a כלי ראשון Kli Rishon and
that has like important implications, you know, even nowadays of how you
sort of see a כלי ראשון. Kli Rishon. One of the רבנים
Rabbeim in the ישיבה Yeshiva says, you know when you're making tea
and which is also very much connected, you know, people sort of
pour it into different vessels to make it into a כלי שלישי
Kli Shlishi or whatever, we assume that as soon as you like
take it from the hot water urn, the hot water urn is
a כלי ראשון Kli Rishon and then the cup is a כלי
שני. Kli Sheni. And then you only have to do it into
one other cup if you want a כלי שלישי. Kli Shlishi. But
Rabbi Levian in the ישיבה, Yeshiva, he thinks that no, the cup
itself becomes a כלי ראשון Kli Rishon because when you open up
the, you know, the spigot, spigot or whatever, and the water flows,
it's still connected to the אש esh in the urn, and it's
a direct flow of water, and part of the water is still
connected to the אש. esh. Your classic כלי שני Kli Sheni? is
you take the vessel off the fire and you pour it, so
when it's going into the second vessel,
the contents of the first vessel are no longer on the fire.
Here when it's going into the cup, the water itself is still
on the fire, right? So and that might make the cup itself
considered connected to this whole arrangement and also part of the כלי
ראשון. Kli Rishon And that seems to be somewhat about what רש"י,
Rashi you know, as understanding in terms of the bathhouse. So that's
important about thinking when does a כלי, Kli, you know, where's that
break line between כלי ראשון Kli Rishon. and כלי שני. Kli Sheni,
Now, more significantly for what do you call it for our purposes
in terms of
the definition of בישול, bishul. so we just have discussed יד סולדת
בו. yad soledet bo,
As I said, יד סולדת בו yad soledes bo in the גמרא
gemara yesterday was more about how hot something has to get to
be considered you're cooking a liquid, not how hot the liquid has
to get to cook other things, but we tend to transfer that
idea. But now we're also introducing a new concept that it has
to be a כלי ראשון. Kli Rishon This is something we're going
to discuss more focused tomorrow: can anything cook in a כלי שני?
Kli Sheni? Now תוספות Tosafos asks the obvious question: if the water
is just as hot in a כלי ראשון keli rishon, as in
a כלי שני, Kli Sheni what would be the logical reason to
say something cooks in a כלי ראשון keli rishon. and doesn't cook
in a כלי שני? keli sheini If you have the same hot
water around it, why should any of that matter? Now there's two
answers to this: one is a like a formalistic distinction and the
other is a try of attempt to give a מציאות metzius answer.
The formalistic distinction, which I actually prefer because it makes it's easier
to understand why there's a strong line between them. Remember I told
you the other day that according to the רמב"ן, Ramban, it's not
considered biblical cooking unless it's directly on the fire. The idea of
כלי ראשון kli rishon would say we don't go that far. You
can cook, I mean, we don't limit it that much, you can
cook even if it's not directly on the fire. But in principle,
I agree with the רמב"ן. Ramban. In principle, I agree that paradigmatic
cooking is cooking something on the fire. If you want to cook
something, you have it over fire, you don't have it on something
that was heated up and removed from the fire. So in principle,
it really should be only on the fire. But you know what?
If it's in the same vessel that was on the fire and
that the stuff was heated up on the fire, and you have
this hot water in this pot and you removed it from the
fire, and then you threw in, there's some actual recipes that talk
about that, right? You take it off the fire and then you
throw in the couscous or something and it like cooks, whatever, right?
You know, because of the hot water. So anyway, because it is
like directly connected to being on the fire, it's in the vessel
that was on the fire and the water was heated up, it's
like on the fire by extension. But it's all because the primary
cooking is on the fire, we extend it a little bit. Anything
in a כלי kli ראשון. Once it's in a second vessel, that's
already completely detached from the reality of being on the fire and
you're exempt. That's a formal distinction of explaining that, and that's one
approach what the difference between כלי kli, ראשון and כלי שני keli
sheini? is. The second approach תוספות Tosafos says is what תוספות Tosafos
says. And תוספות Tosafos says if something goes on the fire, the
walls of the pot retain heat because they got the heat directly
from the fire. And therefore when you remove it from the fire,
they are still keeping the water in the pot warm because they
have retained heat in the walls itself. And therefore, a, it will
stay hotter longer. You could also say it's somewhat more analogous to
what cooking is where the heat is coming from the outside. Whereas
if you pour the hot water into a second pot, what's happening?
It's working the opposite. The heat from the water is dissipating and
going out. So rather than heat coming in and being retained, heat
is being lost and going out once it's in the second vessel.
And תוספות Tosafos says therefore that's why it does not cook. Now
again, within תוספות, Tosafos, you could explain this in a formalistic way.
Formally, to define cooking, heat have to be either retained or coming
in, not just going out. Or you could explain it in a
more practical way. Things won't cook as well because the temperature is
going down rather than if the temperature be retained. The difference is,
the difference is maybe there's some things that can cook easily even
in a second vessel like the couscous example or the tea question.
What if it's a type of thing that can cook easily and
you don't need so much retained heat? You can keep it hot,
let's say the heat is very high, let's say it's scalding, maybe
even a second vessel it will cook. So if you have a
formalistic distinction: no, fundamentally in a formal way we define cooking as
on the fire or related to being on the fire within the
first vessel, or that the heat is still being retained or coming
in. So even practically it cooks, it's not the definition of the
act of cooking in a formal way. That's one approach. The other
approach is: No, in the end of the day it's all the
practical question of: Does the thing get cooked? So in theory there
might be some things that could cook in a כלי שני keli
sheini and that's what we're going to see tomorrow is that question.
Is there a category called קלי הבישול, kalei habishul, things that cook
easily, tea, couscous, whatever. Are there those types of things that can
cook even in a כלי שני? keli sheini? How much is the
difference of כלי ראשון, כלי שני kli sheni. practical and there's some
things that can cook in a כלי שני? How much is it
a formal distinction and we say if it's not related to that
reality of being on the fire then it's not considered biblically cooking
no matter what end result you create? Okay, so this is the
context. So in this דף we have seen the two key primary
criteria
of cooking on Shabbos, or three if you would: בישול אור bishul
or from a fire, not from חמה chama or חמי טבריה; chamei
tverya; number two, יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo in this גמרא
gemara means that that's how hot you've got the water but it's
translated as meaning how hot the water it will be to cook
other things; and number three, כלי ראשון. Yes. Okay, so yes.
What would a microwave be considered?
So okay, microwave is a whole discussion in Rav Moshe, whatever, I'm
not going to get into that. I mentioned the other day that
Rav Moshe considers microwave to be like בישול אור bishul or because
he says it's דרך, derech, but most פוסקים poskim disagree. Anyway, let's
go on. The גמרא gemara says like this. Okay.
אמר רבי זירא, amar rabbi zeira, אנא חזיתיה לרבי אבהו, ana chazitei
l'rabbi abbahu, I saw Rabbi Abbahu דשט באמבטי deshat b'ambati that he
was swimming in a bath. ולא ידענא אי עקר אי לא עקר,
v'lo yadana ei akar ei lo akar, I don't know if he
lifted his feet off the ground or not. So again, presumably this
is not a problem about the water heat, maybe it was חמי
טבריה, chamei tverya, maybe it was a cold bath. But now we're
having another problem, the problem about swimming on Shabbos. So the גמרא
gemara says פשיטא דלא עקר, pshita d'lo akar, obviously he did not
lift his feet off the ground. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braita, לא ישוט אדם בבריכה מלאה מים ואפילו עומדת בחצר, lo
yashut adam b'vreicha meleiah mayim v'afilu omedet b'chatzer, a person should not
swim in a pond filled with water even in a חצר chatzer
which is surrounded, a courtyard which is surrounded by houses, surrounded by
walls, so there's no concern of carrying, but you're not supposed to
swim on Shabbos or on Yom Tov. And the reason there is
because of a concern that you will come to, at least the
way the גמרא gemara, in ביצה beitzah explains it, that you'll come
to make some type of a float or a raft or so
on. So you're not allowed to swim. So maybe you could be
fully immersed if it's not heated before Shabbos or if it's cold
water. But I mean if it's not, you know, if it's not
heated by a fire or if it's cold water, but obviously he
wasn't allowed to swim.
So the גמרא gemara says לא קשיא. lo kashya. הא דלית ליה
גידודי הא דאית ליה גידודי. ha d'leit lei gidudei ha d'it lei
gidudei. There's a difference whether there is a lip around it or
not. What is the issue of the lip? So רש"י Rashi says
one concern of the lip is that if there's no like lip,
it goes sort of you know from the edge and a straight
drop into the hole where the water is, then you'll come to
like you know dig your feet into the dirt right nearby so
you won't fall and maybe that'll make holes or you know it'll
be some type of a problem with you know with manipulating the
earth right nearby. But the other explanation that רש"י Rashi prefers is
not that, is that if it doesn't have a, if it has
a lip it's more like a vessel and if it doesn't have
a lip it's more like it's the ground. And the reason that
you're not allowed to swim, as we said, is a concern that
you'll make flotation devices. Now if you're in a swimming pool there's
not much of a concern you're going to make flotation devices. The
primary area you're concerned you'll make flotation devices is if you're like
swimming in a river. Okay. So therefore the question is at what
stage is a pool considered to be like a river? So the
גמרא Gemara. says it matters if it's got a lip or not.
Let's say you had for example a hot tub, that wouldn't be
like a river, that would be completely within a vessel. So even
if you have a pool in the ground, if it's got like
a lip at the edge, you know, then it's not like if
it's just a hole in the ground that's more similar to a
river, okay, although it's true it's a pool, but if it's got
a lip on it then it's more like a vessel and therefore
it's not the same גזירה gezeira of swimming in a river where
we're concerned you'll make flotation devices. So according to this you are
allowed to swim in a pool as long as it has a
lip around the edge, and that's why ספרדים Sefardim actually do swim,
as long as it's not water heated from before Shabbat, it's not
heated water, so that's why ספרדים Sefardim actually swim in a pool
on, on Shabbos. And actually you know if you had a case
where it was, which was heated by the sun, you use some
type of a, you know, of a mirrors or whatever to concentrate
solar heat and it was בישול חמה, bishul chama, you could even
swim in a heated pool as long as it was not heated
by a fire even from before Shabbos. אשכנזים Ashkenazim as I said
in a פוסט-גמרא post-gemara גזירה gezeira already going back at least a
thousand years, I think, yes, about a thousand years,
maybe less, maybe 800, anyway, we do not fully immerse ourselves in
water on Shabbos, even cold water, probably somewhat as an extension of
what the גמרא Gemara said also because of a concern that, a,
the גמרא Gemara said even if you're in a חצר, chatzer, because
if you're not in a חצר chatzer you get out of the
pool and you're dripping water so you're walking, you're carrying the water
on your body, but even if you're in a חצר chatzer there's
problems about squeezing your hair and squeezing a towel. So basically for
the אשכנזים Ashkenazim מנהג minhag that follows גמרא, Gemara we do not
even fully immerse ourselves in water, even cold water, but according to
the גמרא Gemara it's okay as long as it's more like a
pool and less like a river. You had a question, Michael?
Does it matter so the two things going on here, one is
the carrying water,
which
is it's also—
Was there something discussed recently about the size, the maximum size of
a כלי and a swimming pool's going to be way larger than
that?
Right, but the here, here point is that sometimes we do consider
big כלים keilim to be כלים keilim but anyway here the point
is primarily that it's just less, it's not that it's more of
a כלי, well it's somewhat but it's more the point is that
it's less like a river. So once it's not in that river
category, פשיטא. pishita.
Okay, and the lakes are okay then? Yeah.
I
thought the problem with swimming was you can't wet your clothes on
שבת.
Shabbat Well no, I mean you can wet your clothes as long
as you don't squeeze them out. So you know, so but that's
a lot of why the אשכנזים Ashkenazim don't like it is because
you'll come to squeeze things out. You mean you'll get stuff wet
even, it's true that, you mean laundering. That's true, that's true, yeah,
yeah, yeah, that's true. So right, that's true, that's true. If so
first of all you know it's a general question why can you
dry your hands on a towel on שבת? Shabbos You're getting the
towel wet. So if you're doing it דרך לכלוך, derech lichluch, if
it's in the way of getting something soiled, you know, then it's,
then it's, then it's even though it's getting it wet it's not
considered a part of the process of cleaning. So if you're drying
your body with a towel, and we do, you can dry things
with a towel on שבת, Shabbos, it's not considered cleaning. So the
question is more like the bathing suit. But if the bathing suit
is you know a type of what do they material do they
use like Lycra or whatever they use, so basically there's no like
there's no laundering by that because it's non-absorbent. It's sort of like
you can put, you can, you can clean your glasses with water
or your shoes with glasses with water. You only, it's really like
woven material that it's considered to be cleaning. So the type of
material they make a bathing suit out of is not a problem.
So that's a good point back then. What? Yeah, I guess if
you had a cloth bathing suit that could be an issue. But
they probably just swam in the nude.
Right,
exactly. That's a good question. You know you're right if you actually,
how much is it specifically the lip or other types of qualities
also? So they tend to emphasize the criterion in the גמרא. Gemara.
I haven't really, since it's not so relevant for אשכנזים Ashkenazim I
really haven't seen the תשובה teshuvah literature about that.
But what if you swim with your head above water, does that
count as a פסיק רישא?
psik reisha? Yeah, I mean I think so. I think
כל גופו. kol gufo. I, you know, I mean the גמרא Gemara
yesterday spoke about leaving one limb outside and said that it was
still in the גזירה gezeirah and I assume the same is true
even for the אשכנזים Ashkenazim מנהג. minhag. Exactly what the cut-off point
is I'm not sure but I think keeping your head above water
is somehow it doesn't get, it doesn't solve the problem
on שבת Shabbat, or יום טוב.
Yom Tov. For אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, correct. Yeah.
Can you use tissue to, to wet your...? Yeah, because you know
yeah, because you're not...
alright. I mean because also that's דרך לכלוך. derech lichluch. Okay so
now picking up finally getting to today's דף מ"א. דאמר רבי זירא,
Damar Reb Zeira, אנא חזיתיה לרבי אבהו ana chazisye leRabbi Abbahu שהניח
ידו sheniach yado כנגד פניו של מטה keneged panav shel mata ולא
ידענא vlo yadana אי נגע אי לא נגע. ee naga ee lo
naga. So now that we're talking about bathing, so we have another
statement that says says רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira says I and it
was also before was רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira seeing רבי אבהו Rabbi
Abbahu in the אמבטי, ambati, so here again it's רבי זירא Rabira
Zeira seeing רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. I saw רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu
that when he was going into swimming whether it was שבת Shabbat.
or maybe even the weekday it sounds like he put his hand
in front of his you know you know in his genital area.
So and I don't know when he was doing that if he
happened to touch his genitals or not. So he was doing it
out of privacy but now we're concerned you know because of issues
associated with masturbation so even just touching the genitals should be a
problem. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא דלא נגע, pishita d'lo naga,
obviously he was careful not to touch. דתניא, Detanya, רבי אליעזר אומר
Rabbi Eliezer omer כל האוחז באמה ומשתין כאילו מביא מבול לעולם. kol
ha'ochez b'amah umashkin k'ilu meivi mabul l'olam. If somebody holds their you
know holds themselves when they're urinating it's like they bring a flood
to the world so you're not supposed to touch and even of
a concern that even without intentional masturbation it'll lead to erection and
thoughts and whatever and זרע לבטלה. zera levatala. So obviously he must
have been careful. So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אביי Abaye said you
know what? It's a little different here. עשו כבולשת. Asu k'boleshet. It's
like the when the troops come into the city. You're too distracted
by other things to be worrying about some things. דתנן, Detnan, we
taught in the משנה Mishnah בולשת שנכנסה לעיר boleshet shenichnesa l'ir if
these troops came into a city בשעת שלום besha'at shalom at the
time when it's peace meaning that they're not in the middle of
fighting a war and running away from other troops. So
then חביות פתוחות אסורות, chaviyot petuchot asurot, open barrels of wine are
forbidden because you're afraid they helped themselves to some wine and these
are non-Jews. סתומות מותרות, Stumot mutarot, closed barrels are permissible. בשעת מלחמה
Besha'at milchama and they're in the middle of a war and whether
they're presumably on the offense or the defense they're still too distracted
by the war to stop and take some wine. So אלו ואלו
מותרות eilu v'eilu mutarot even open barrels are okay לפי שאין פנאי
לנסך lefi she'ein penai l'nasach they don't have time to to do
a ניסוך nisuch to pour out for עבודה זרה, avoda zara, maybe
they don't even have time to drink it not clear but certainly
they don't have time to do a ניסוך. nisuch. אלמא Alma regardless
what you see is כיון דבעיתי kivan d'bi'isi since they're afraid לא
מנסכי lo menaschi they don't do the ניסוך היין. nisuch hayayin. הכא
נמי Hacha nami here too כיון דבעית kivan d'bayis since you're afraid
you know you're exposed you're in public and therefore you're doing it
out of concern
of
embarrassment. Where you're covering yourself because you're in public. So Gemara says:
והכא מאי בעיתותא, v'hacha mai bisusa, what is the fright here? So
actually I jumped ahead, I said it was a fear of being
in public but the Gemara says: בעיתותא דנהרא. bisusa de-nahara. You're afraid
because you're going into the river, so you're like afraid about, I
don't know, just safety issues. So the Gemara says: איני, והאמר רבי
אבא אמר רב הונא אמר רב, ini, v'ha-amar Rabbi Abba amar Rav
Huna amar Rav, כל המניח ידו כנגד פניו של מטה kol hamanich
yado k'neged panav she-lemata כאילו כופר בבריתו של אברהם אבינו, k'ilu kofer
bivriso shel Avraham Avinu, that even if you if you put your
even forgetting the issue about about what do you call it about
touching yourself, but just covering yourself up in front you know of
your genital is like you're denying the covenant of אברהם אבינו, Avraham
Avinu, you're hiding the fact that you're circumcised, you know particularly in
the in the Roman context and the Hellenistic context where it might
have been an embarrassment to be seen in public uncircumcised, I mean
circumcised, you know walking naked uncircumcised athletes and so on. So that's
maybe how it was interpreted. So the Gemara says okay so the
Gemara says so how did he do it regardless? לא קשיא, lo
kashya, says the Gemara, it's not difficult. הא כי נחית, הא כי
סליק. ha kinachis, ha kisali. Difference whether you're going down to the
river or coming up from the river. When you're going down to
the river then you know your back is to the people, nobody
sees you. So then you shouldn't be covering yourself up because it
looks like you're embarrassed that you're that you're circumcised. When you're coming
up from the river and your front is towards people who'd be
walking nearby, then it is appropriate to cover yourself out up out
of issues of modesty. Okay so it could be that now by
the time the Gemara gets to this, this is also the בעיתותא,
bisusa, the fear, the fear is being exposed, not the fear of
the river, but you don't know, maybe the Gemara is still basing
itself on the previous answer that regardless your thoughts are distracted not
just because of privacy concerns but because you know you're just concerned
about you're going into the river. Anyway, so the Gemara says so
that's why it was allowed because he wasn't facing the people, because
he was facing the people, that's why it was allowed. So then
now the Gemara says like this,
כי הא דרבא ki ha de-Rava like Rava שחי, shachi, he would
go swimming and I'm sorry שחי, shachi, he would bend down, ורבי
זירא זקיף. v'Rabbi Zeira zaki. So Rava would sort of like crouch
over so his genital would not be exposed, but Rabbi Zeira would
walk straight up and he would not be he would be afraid
that by covering himself up it would look like he's embarrassed that
he's circumcised. The Gemara doesn't make it clear whether was that when
they were both facing the people or when they were both not
facing the people. But anyway it says that there are different concerns
here, somewhat competing concerns, one of modesty the other of denying one's
circumcision and therefore the way it resolves is here we have different
practices but the way the Gemara resolves it is whether you're facing
the people or not.
Now the Gemara moved on quickly didn't it?
Yeah I know that was a very quick move wasn't it? Because
it was Rabbi Abba talking about Rabbi Zeira talking about something he
saw about Rabbi Abba and swimming and on שבת Shabbat. and so
on. Oh by the way right. Now we're going to have one
final statement about Rabbi Zeira since we're about in Rabbi Zeira, so
just you
know רבנן דבי רב אשי, Rabbanan d'vei Rav Ashi, the rabbis of
the house of Rav Ashi, the rabbinical students, כי כנחתי ki kanchasi
זקפי, zaki, כי כסלקי ki kasali שחי. shachi. And
here is exactly how they reconciled this different approach. When they would
be going when they would go up from the river and they'd
be facing people they would bend down so it would not be
exposed. When they were going down to the river and therefore they
were not facing the people they would be straight up so as
not to be seen as denying the circumcision. Okay.
I reverse it anyway it says
when they went down they were straight up, when they came up
they were bent over. Question?
Yes. I wonder if the different locations these Rabbis might have to
do with this because the Greek influence was much much less in
בבל Bavel and there was a big deal about being circumcised in
the Greek and Roman bathhouses but it wasn't as big a deal
from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to בבל Bavel and Rabbi Zeira went
the other direction.
And
the other
I think the other rabbis here are all from So
you're trying to say that Rabbi Zeira that it was זקיף zaki
was because he was in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and Rava that was שחי shachi was because he was in בבל.
Bavel.
That's I wonder about that.
That's a nice פשט, p'shat, it's a nice פשט p'shat because it
is very true that the primary concern we would think the Gemara
would be concerned about would be the modesty issue, so this idea
of not to see to be seen like you're hiding your circumcision
is a heightened concern in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and that's consistent
with Rabbi Zeira, that's very nice. Okay. Now the Gemara says now
we're going to talk about Rabbi Zeira actually going to ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. רבי זירא הוה קמשתמיט מרב יהודה. Rabbi Zeira hava kameishtameit
mi-Rav Yehuda. Rabbi Zeira was avoiding Rav Yehuda, we actually had this
already in ברכות. Berachos. Why was Rabbi Zeira avoiding Rav Yehuda? דבעי
למיסק לארץ ישראל, de-ba'i l'meiska l'Eretz Yisrael, Rabbi Zeira wanted to make
עליה, aliyah, he wanted to go to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, and
he was avoiding Rav Yehuda because
Rav Yehuda And it said,
בבלה יובאו ושמה יהיו. Bavel'ah yuva'u ve'shammah yihyu. It says עד יום
העלותי אותם, ad yom ha'alosi osam, I think,
until the day that I bring them out. And this as we
know even until today, some people believe there's gonna be no going
back to Israel and no sense of משיח Mashiach until it's all
miraculous and comes straight from heaven. So that was רב יהודה'ס Rav
Yehuda's point: you stay here until there's an obvious משיח, Mashiach, whereas
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira felt it was appropriate to go to ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, either for תורה Torah or just for its own
sake. So anyway he was avoiding רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, he didn't
want to have רב יהודה Rav Yehuda give him a hard time.
So אמר, amar, he said, but before I go, I should at
least try to be at least get one last thing from him
before I go. איזיל ואשמע מיניה מלתא ואיתי ואיזיל. Izil ve'eshma mineih
milta ve'eisei ve'izil.
Let me go and hear from him a little word of תורה
Torah before I actually go and leave to ישראל. Yisrael.
אזל, Azal, he went, אשכחיה, ashkachieih, he saw him, דקאי בבי בני,
de'ka'ei b'vei banei, he was in the bathhouse, וקאמר ליה לשמעיה, ve'ka'amar
leih l'shamaieih, and he said to his attendant, הביאו לי נתר
הביאו לי מסרק, Havi'u li neter havi'u li masrek, bring me a
lye which is like soap, bring me, bring me a comb. פתחו
פומיכו ואפיקו הבלא, Pitchu pumieichu ve'afiku havla,
open up your mouths and let the hot air of the bathhouse
come in and let the hot air inside of you like good
air in, bad air out. רש"י Rashi also says you'll sweat so
the bad stuff will come out through the sweat. והביאו לי ואשקיוני
מיא דבי בני, ve'havi'u li ve'ashkyuni maya d'vei banei,
and also get me some of the water from the bathhouse, the
water heated up so that I could drink it. I hope it's
before other people bathed in it. Okay. אמר, Amar, so then רבי
זירא Rabbi Zeira said, אלמלא באתי אלא לשמוע דבר זה דיי, Ilmalei
basi ella lishmo'a davar zeh dayi,
if I hadn't come but just to hear this one thing of
what he was telling his attendant in the bathhouse, דיי, dayi, that
would be sufficient. Oh, I learned so much תורה Torah just from
hearing him talk to his attendant in the bathhouse. So the גמרא'ס
Gemara's going to say, what תורה Torah did you figure it out
from that? So it says like this: בשלמא הביאו נתר הביאו מסרק,
Bishlama havi'u neter havi'u masrek,
I understand when he says bring me the soap and bring me
the comb, קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, what did he learn
from that? דברים של חול מותר לאמרם בלשון הקודש, Devarim shel chol
mutar l'omram bi'leshon ha'kodesh, that you can say secular things in Hebrew
even in a bathhouse. As we said before, the problem is saying
תורה Torah regardless of the language is a problem in the bathhouse,
but saying things in Hebrew even if they're as long as they're
not תורה Torah it's totally fine. So that's one thing you learn
from him. פתחו פומיכו ואפיקו הבלא נמי, Pitchu pumieichu ve'afiku havla nami,
open up your mouths and let the bad air come out or
come out through your sweat, כשמואל, k'Shmuel, like שמואל, Shmuel, דאמר שמואל,
de'amar Shmuel, הבלא מפיק הבלא, havla mafik havla, air takes out air.
So the good air comes in and the bad air goes out.
Okay, so that's an important health principle to learn. אלא אשקיוני מיא
דבי בני מאי מעליותא, Ella ashkyuni maya d'vei banei mai ma'alyusa, drink
from the hot water heated up for the bathhouse, what's the good
part about that? דתניא, De'tanya, why is that an important thing? אכל
ולא שתה, Achal v'lo shasa, if somebody eats without drinking, אכילתו דם,
achilaso dam, his eating is like blood, meaning it turns somehow into
blood, it's bad for his health, וזהו תחילת חולי מעיים, ve'zehu techilas
choli me'ayim, and this is what leads to the beginning of digestive
problems, eating without drinking. אכל ולא הלך ארבע אמות, Achal v'lo halach
arba amos, if you ate without then afterwards walking four אמות amos
to get the stuff to digest after you
walked, אכילתו מרקבת, achilaso merakeves, your food starts to rot, וזהו תחילת
ריח רע, ve'zehu techilas rei'ach ra, and that's what leads to bad
breath. הנצרך לנקביו ואכל, Ha'nitzrach l'nekavav v'achal, if you have to go
to the bathroom, presumably it means you have to defecate and you're
eating even though you need to be going to the bathroom right
now, דומה לתנור שהסיקוהו על גבי אפרו, domeh l'sannur she'hisikuhu al gabbei
afro, getting back maybe to the theme of this פרק perek about
a תנור tannur and ashes, it's like lighting up an oven without
having swept out the ashes. So it's got all this waste product
in it and you're trying to start a fire on top of
it, and presumably also the fire won't start well because it's got
all the ashes underneath it. So you have all of this waste
you have to get rid of and you're adding food on top
of it. וזהו תחילת ריח זוהמא, Ve'zehu techilas ריח זוהמא rei'ach zuhama,
and that leads to like a
bad body odor. רחץ בחמין ולא שתה מהן, Rachatz b'chamin v'lo shasa
me'hen, this is getting at finally...
ריח רע וריח זוהמא,
rei'ach
ra ve'rei'ach zuhama, bad breath and body odor. רחץ בחמין ולא שתה
מהן, Rachatz b'chamin v'lo shasa me'hen, if you washed in hot water
but then you did not drink from the hot water, which is
what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was telling his
attendant, דומה לתנור שהסיקוהו מבחוץ ולא הסיקוהו מבפנים, domeh l'sannur she'hisikuhu mi'bachutz
v'lo hisikuhu mi'pifnim, it's like an oven that you lit it on
the outside and you didn't lit it on the inside. You applied
the hot water on the outside but not the hot water on
the inside. And of course for an oven to be effective you
need the fire on the inside as well. So you think a
bathing is so healthy, but it's only healthy if you also drink
hot water as well. Again, it's not exactly clear why of the
bathhouse, again, I hope it was the clean water before it was
used. But anyway, okay. So anyway,
okay. רחץ בחמין ולא נשתטף בצונן, Rachatz b'chamin v'lo nishtatef b'tzonen, now
if you bathed in hot water and you didn't do a cold
shower afterwards, דומה לברזל שהכניסוהו לאור ולא הכניסוהו לצונן, domeh l'varzel she'hichnisuhu
l'or v'lo hichnisuhu l'tzonen, it's like hot iron that you put into
fire and then you didn't put it into cold water after, and
the cold water hardens the iron after it's been molded in the
heat. I'm sorry, not hot water, you put it into fire and
then you didn't put it into cold water after. So here you
got your whole body in hot water, but you need the cold
water after to do the final job for health purposes. רחץ ולא
סך Rachatz v'lo sach if you bathed and didn't put oil on
afterwards דומה למים אגבי חבית domeh l'mayim agabei chavit it's like water
on the outside of a barrel where it just runs off. So
therefore you need the oil to help again maybe preserve the health
benefits of the washing. So I learned from him these important health
purposes. So it's interesting right he didn't learn any huge תורה, Torah,
right, but this more of the points about health and about speaking
in the bathhouse he learned about speaking תורה, Torah, speaking weekday things
in the Hebrew language maybe again is particularly poignant because here he
is on the one hand, you know, he's violating his רבי principle
about not making עליה Aliyah and going to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and you know, you might understand that this would be like a
point where he might want to sort of, you know, focus on,
on the sense like of creating a greater sense of distance and
separation, you know, and actually, you know, I think it's very poignant
that there's this sense of like dependency and he hangs on every
single word and even like these almost trivial teachings he has to
try to grab, you know, the last little bit before he goes.
So he's able, you know, and at the same time he's able
to go against him on this principal issue about making עליה, Aliyah,
but it doesn't mean that he's like trying to, you know, fully
distance himself from him.
Okay, so on this speaking on the לשון הקודש, Lashon HaKodesh, was
this interpreted by religious elements that were opposed to re-establishment of Hebrew
in the modern era? Was this interpreted in a general sense or
just in the bathhouse or was that a
by the people that were opposed to
speaking Hebrew as a modern language?
But this is saying that it's allowed, ומותר לדבר בלשון הקודש. u'mutar
l'daber b'lashon hakodesh. Yes,
so the opposite. All right. So anyway, all right. So now the
גמרא Gemara goes on, next משנה. Mishnah. So that was an interesting
digression but again, very important principles we learned is number one, it's
cooking only with a fire, תולדות חמה is דרבנן, תולדות אור toldos
or is still דאורייתא. d'oraisa. It's cooking presumably,
you need יד סולדת בו yad soledet bo if you're cooking liquids
and to be considered that you cooked the liquid, and as I
said we learned from there we assume from there also that that's
how hot the liquid is to cook other things. And number three
is the idea of a כלי ראשון as opposed to a כלי
שני. Okay, now we go on.
Always make your bathwater...
Exactly. מוליאר הגרוף שותין הימנו בשבת. Mulyar hagaruph shotin heimenu b'Shabbos. If
you have a מוליאר, mulyar, which is some type of a, of
a container of water which we'll see that they would put maybe
coals in a, like it's sort of like a thermos. But imagine
a thermos, we have, our thermoses are like surrounded by some liquid
in the second layer, right, that keeps it warm or cold or
whatever. Yeah, a vacuum. A vacuum, is that what does it? Know
the joke, you know the joke they say about a thermos? It
keeps cold things cold and hot things hot. But how does it
know? So anyway, so okay, so anyway. So this was like a
thermos where you had a second layer that actually had coals around
it to keep the stuff inside hot. Okay? Is this the drawing
of it? Okay, so this מוליאר, mulyar, which is גרוף, garuph, so
this is like the difference about sweeping out an oven and keeping
fire on it. If it has the ashes removed, שותין הימנו בשבת,
shotin heimenu b'Shabbos, then you can use it on שבת, Shabbat. even
if it's retained, you know, it's retaining the heat and it's keeping
something hot, but it's okay because the ashes have been removed, the
coals have been removed. אנטיכי, Antikhi, an אנטיכי antikhi which is a
similar thing of keeping things hot, although this might have been made
of metal, another version רש"י Rashi says is that the coals were
at the bottom not at the side. So this is something which
is more like the תנור. tanur. Remember the תנור tanur which has,
retains its heat more than a כירה, kirah, we don't allow it
even if it's swept out. And the same is true about this
אנטיכי, antikhi, אף על פי שגרופה, aph al pi she'gruphah, even if
it's swept out, אין שותין הימנו, ein shotin heimenu, you cannot drink
from it.
So the גמרא Gemara says the following, היכי דמי מוליאר הגרוף, heichi
dami mulyar hagaruph, what is this מוליאר mulyar which is גרוף, garuph,
which is okay to use?
תנא מים מבפנים וגחלים מבחוץ, Tana mayim mibifnim u'gechalim mibachutz, water on
the inside and coals around the outside, that is this מוליאר. mulyar.
And again, it retains its heat but not so much so it's
okay as long as it's swept out. אנטיכי, Antikhi, what's an אנטיכי?
antikhi? רבא אמר בי כרי. Rava amar bei kirei. It's a בי
כרי bei kirei which רש"י Rashi says means it's like a little
insert inside the oven itself. So therefore it's very very hot. רב
נחמן בר יצחק אמר בי דודי, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar bei
dudi, which רש"י Rashi says again means something where the coals are
on the bottom, not on the side, but also some type of
a vessel. מאן דאמר בי דודי כל שכן בי כרי, Man d'amar
bei dudi kol sheken bei kirei, if בי דודי bei dudi is
a problem certainly this בי כרי bei kirei which is literally in
the oven, ומאן דאמר בי כרי אבל בי דודי לא, u'man d'amar
bei kirei aval bei dudi lo, בי דודי bei dudi is not
a problem because it's not as hot. תני כוותיה דרב נחמן, Tani
k'vatieh d'Rav Nachman, it taught like רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, אנטיכי אף
על פי שגרופה וקטומה, antikhi aph al pi she'gruphah u'ktumah, an אנטיכי
antikhi even if it's swept out and the ashes are put on
it, so אין שותין הימנו, ein shotin heimenu, you cannot drink from
it on שבת, מפני שנחושתה מחממתה, mipnei she'nechushtah mechamematah, because its, it's
metal, it's copper, it keeps it warm, retains heat more. Or רש"י
says נחושתה nechushtah can mean the floor, because the floor is being
heated, it retains its heat more. So this is direct parallel to
the כירה kirah and the תנור. tanur. The כירה kirah you sweep
out you can use it, the תנור tanur you cannot. Here too
in one case you can, in one case you cannot, presumably a
similar type of a גזירה gezeirah that you'll come to either stir
the coals or that it'll look like cooking on שבת. תוספות Tosafot
says another concern, that you want to use this hot water to
mix with wine and will the water that's kept in here be
so hot that it'll cook the wine? So in the first case
it would it won't get that hot and it's okay, the second
case where it's presumed that it'll be remain יד סולדת בו yad
soledet bo and very hot, and therefore it'll be a problem to
mix it with wine. Yes?
I presume that we פוסקים pasken that modern hot pots are for
water are like the מויאר Moyar and not the אנטיכי? Antiki?
What do you mean by a hot pot? You mean a waterer?
An urn. An urn? Yeah, well, well that's an interesting question about
the urn and about how do you address the גרוף וקטום garf
vekatum issue. I mean, you know, we are, you know, we do
what do you call it, we yes, we do assume that it's
like the מויאר, Moyar, that is true, but the question is how
do you address the גרוף וקטום, garf vekatum, right? So it could
just be that there's no knob, there's no way to adjust it,
and then you know it and you know does raise these issues,
right? Because if you also need to cover the flame, the flames
in there are already pre-covered. So the general assumption is since there's
no way to adjust it that's okay. It's actually an interesting question
that are people more מחמיר machmir by those urns and require something
more to make it considered to be a היכר? heker? Point is
also you have no access to the fire as opposed to many
other cases. It's similar that way to the what do you call
it, to the crock pot. And I know by crock pot people
are מחמיר, machmir, there are people that are מחמיר machmir to put
a whole metal on the inside of a crock pot. It's a
good question why nobody, I haven't heard of anybody having that חומרה
chumra by a urn.
As long as there's no knob there shouldn't, it should be.
That's true. I mean a crock pot does have a knob, right?
Okay, so and but even people that remove the knob still insist
on putting a metal insert in a crock pot. Anyway, there are
people. המיחם שפינהו. Hamicham shepinahu. Now we're getting back to also aspects
of cooking. So you have this hot water pot, excellent example, right?
A hot water urn, a kettle, that you removed it. Now it
could mean you removed it off the fire, it could mean you
removed the water from it, that'll be a דעה deiah in the
גמרא. Gemara לא יתן לתוכו צונן Lo yitein letocho tzonin do not
put in it cold water בשביל שיחמו bishvil sheyechamu so that they'll
get heated up, אבל נותן הוא לתוכו או לתוך הכוס כדי להפשירן,
aval noten hu letocho o letoch hakos kedei lehafshiran, you put water
in it to warm up, to sort of to you know to
dissolve or to remove or to remove the chill, and similarly into
a vessel, but you cannot actually try to get it hot. So
it seems like the difference here is what we spoke about yesterday
about putting water or oil in front of a fire. You can
put it there if you want to just get it to dissolve
or to remove the chill, you cannot put it there if you're
going to get it so hot that it'll get יד סולדת בו
yad soledet bo, which will be a type of a cooking. So
how do you know the difference? Presumably the difference is, well, how
hot is this thing, will the water I put in get יד
סולדת בו yad soledet bo or not? But it's a funny משנה
Mishnah because the משנה Mishnah didn't tell me what scenarios are okay,
what are not okay. Don't put water in it that'll get hot,
but you can put water in it that'll just you know warm
up. Where's the line? What's the difference? So let's take a look
at what the גמרא Gemara says. מאי קאמר? Mai ka'amar? What's it
say? What do you mean don't put in so it'll get hot,
put in so it'll warm up?
What can you do, what can't you do? So אמר רב אמר
רב אדא בר מתנה הכי קאמר, Amar Rav Amar Rav Adda bar
Matnah hachi ka'amar, this is what it means. המיחם שפינה ממנו מים,
Hamicham shepinah mimenu mayim, you have this hot water kettle that you
removed the water from it, it was hot water on the fire,
you removed the hot water from it, לא יתן לתוכו מים מועטים
lo yitein letocho mayim muatim do not put a little water into
this very hot kettle בשביל שיחמו bishvil sheyechamu
because a little water, the water will get heated up and maybe
it'll get יד סולדת yad soledet. בו, אבל נותן לתוכו מים מרובים
aval noten letocho mayim merubim you can put a lot of water
into it כדי להפשירן, kedei lehafshiran, that'll just get them warm, it
won't get them hot. Okay, so the basic difference is, you see,
you didn't think we were going to finish today. תוספות Tosfos saved
us. The basic difference is, as you know, if you have something
very hot you put a little bit in, so the little thing
gets heated up. You put a lot in, the lot of cold
water cools everything all at once, so it cools everything else down.
So the basic difference is a little you'll get the thing will
get יד סולדת בו where it's a problem, a lot everything will
cool down and you'll be okay. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, how can you put a lot of cold water into
this really hot pot? והלא מצרף? Vahalo mitsaref? Are you not basically
what? מצרף. mitsaref. מצרף, mitsaref, right. Well, what's the English word for
מצרף? mitsaref?
Smelting, tempering. Is that what we call tempering when you put cold
water? Right, so exactly what we described before about you know if
you take a hot shower and you don't take and you don't
do a hot shower after a hot bath. It's like you heated
up the metal and then you put in the cold water. So
putting a hot metal in cold water afterwards is like the finishing
of making a vessel, right? Because it's cooling it off after the
heat and that like hardens it. So the גמרא Gemara says now
you would think that's the first time you made a vessel. Okay,
I don't know enough about the מציאות metzius of these vessels at
these times, maybe it was an ongoing process that continued to harden
the vessel after it got heated up, you put in no, you
don't think so? Anyway, the גמרא Gemara thinks that that's a problem,
that even an existing vessel once it's heated up if you immerse
it in cold water that hardens it and that's a type of
and that's a problem on שבת. Maybe biblical, maybe rabbinic, sounds like
it's biblical, that's a problem on שבת. So how could you pour,
fill, dump a ton of cold water in it one time into
this empty vessel that's מצרף, mitsaref, that hardens this hot empty vessel?
How is that allowed? So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is, the גמרא
says this is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon דאמר דבר שאינו מתכוין מותר,
d'amar davar she'eino mitkaven mutar,
that you're not intending to do. And presumably, although רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says if it'll necessarily happen it's a problem, presumably here won't
necessarily have that effect of hardening it. It just might have that
effect, so we'll be okay with it because it's רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon and it won't necessarily happen. So the גמרא says מתקיף לה
אביי, matkif la Abaye, אביי Abaye asks, I don't like that read
of the משנה. Mishnah. מיחם שפינה ממנו מים תני? meicham shepina mimenu
mayim tanni? It doesn't say a hot water urn that you emptied
the water out from it. מיחם שפינהו קתני, meicham shepinahu ktanni, it
says a hot water urn that you removed it, not you removed
the water from it, but you removed it. So what does it
mean? אלא אמר אביי הכי קאמר, ella amar Abaye hachi ka'amar, this
is what it means. המיחם שפינהו ויש בו מים חמים, hameicham shepinahu
veyesh bo mayim chamim, you removed the hot water urn or that
water whatever kettle from the fire. You understand the two interpretations? It
says you removed that water urn, the kettle. So does it mean
you removed the water from the kettle, or does it mean you
removed the kettle from the fire? So אביי Abaye says it means
you removed the kettle from the fire. And what do you do
in that case? לא יתן לתוכו מים מועטים. lo yiten letocho mayim
mu'atim. So basically, the scenario is, in the first version, you had
an empty, very hot kettle. In the second scenario, you have a
very hot kettle with hot water in it. So what do you
do with it? So here's what he says: לא יתן לתוכו מים
מועטים, lo yiten letocho mayim mu'atim, you can't put a little water
into this hot water in the kettle, בשביל שיחמו, bishvil sheyeichammu, that
it should heat up. אבל נותן לתוכו מים מרובין כדי להפשירן, aval
noten letocho mayim merubin kedei lehafshiran, but you could put in a
lot of water at one time because that'll just warm it but
it won't heat it up. So basically, it's the same difference: a
little water, it'll get, the little water will get hot and that'll
be בישול. A lot of water it'll get warm but not hot
and you're okay. The difference is that he's dealing with a vessel
that already has hot water in it as opposed to an empty
vessel. And the reason אביי's Abaye reasoning is preferred in addition to
the grammatical point is because he doesn't have to deal with the
problem of מצרף. mitzaref. מצרף mitzaref is you have a very hot
vessel that's empty that you immerse in water. And therefore, that was
a problem if you read that you emptied the vessel from the
water. But according to אביי's Abaye read that there is hot water
in the vessel right now, even when you add cold water, it's
not מצרף. mitzaref. מצרף mitzaref is when you immerse a hot empty
hot vessel into water. So then אביי Abaye adds, and therefore, ומיחם
שפינה ממנו מים, umeicham shepina mimenu mayim, if it really is empty,
לא יתן לתוכו מים lo yiten letocho mayim כל עיקר kol ikkar
at all, מפני שמצרף, mipnei shemetzaref, because then that will be like
a tempering. Okay, so they basically agree to the point: a little
water will get it hot, no good, a lot of water will
be warm, it's okay as far as the water's concerned. But the
issue is, if the vessel is empty, will that be okay or
not because will that be like tempering? Okay, and do we like
רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? And so אביי, Abaye, who is concerned about
tempering, says, רבי יהודה היא, Rabbi Yehuda hi, and this is רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, דאמר דבר שאינו מתכוין אסור, d'amar davar she'eino mitkaven
assur, that even if you're not intending. Okay, so you all got
it? The idea is if the vessel is empty and it's very
hot and it's a metal vessel, then there's a possibility that by
immersing it in water or pouring water into it, it'll temper it.
But you're not intending to do that. So if you're a רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon man, דבר שאינו מתכוין מותר, davar she'eino mitkaven mutar,
you're okay, and therefore you could read the משנה Mishnah that way,
that the vessel is empty. If you're a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
man, דבר שאינו מתכוין davar she'eino mitkaven is אסור, assur, then it's
no good, and therefore you have to read the משנה Mishnah not
that the vessel is empty but the vessel already has hot water
in it. As far as the בישול is concerned, if you had
a little bit of cold water, that's a problem because then that
water will get very hot, it'll be בישול. If you had a
lot of cold water, that's okay, the water will just get warm,
not hot, and you're okay.
Ravi asked a question, unless I'm mistaken, wouldn't even רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon say if it's פסיק רישא? psik reisha?
Yes, but I said it's not פסיק רישא, psik reisha, it won't
necessarily happen. אמר רב, Rav so said רב, Rav לא שנו אלא
להפשיר אבל לצרף אסור. lo shannu ella lehafshier aval letzaref assur. So
now it sounds like they're just repeating what they said before. רב
says it's okay as long as you're just trying to warm up
the water. But if you're actually tempering the vessel, that's a problem.
ושמואל אמר אפילו לצרף נמי מותר. u'Shmuel amar afilu letzaref nami mutar.
Even to temper it, it's okay. Sounds like even intentionally. So the
גמרא says לצרף לכתחילה מי שרי? letzaref l'chatchila mi shari? Since when
are you allowed to לכתחילה l'chatchila
temper a vessel if you're intending to do it? אלא אי איתמר
הכי איתמר, ella ee itmar hachi itmar, here's how it should have
been said. אמר רב לא שנו אלא שיעור להפשיר אבל שיעור לצרף
אסור. lo shannu ella shiur lehafshier aval shiur letzaref assur. It's only
allowed if you put into it a small amount of water, not
enough that it will really temper the vessel, then it's okay. But
if you put into it a lot of cold water, then that
is enough to temper the vessel, that is a problem.
Okay,
so ושמואל אמר אפילו שיעור לצרף מותר. u'Shmuel amar afilu shiur letzaref
mutar. Even if there's a lot of cold water and it could
do the job and it could possibly temper the vessel, that's still
allowed. Why? So again, this difference: רב is holding like רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, he's concerned that once it has enough water that it
could potentially temper the vessel, a lot of cold water, that's a
problem. And שמואל Shmuel is not concerned because you're not intending to
temper it. So the גמרא says למימרא, l'meimra, this sounds like דשמואל
כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה? deShmuel keRabbi Shimon svera leh? שמואל Shmuel holds
like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says that if you're not intending,
it's allowed. So is that really true? So then the גמרא will
pick up with this tomorrow about whether שמואל Shmuel holds like רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon or not. So again, the basic difference is a
little water if it'll
get
יד סולדת. So if you're but not necessarily. So if you're רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you don't care because you're not intending it won't
definitely happen, you could fill it up with as much cold water
as you want, not a problem. But if you're רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda and you do care, even if it tempers it even if
you weren't intending to to do it, then the only scenario would
be that you didn't totally fill it with cold water. But to
totally fill it with cold water which has the potential of tempering,
that would not be allowed according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
we will see tomorrow to what degree שמואל Shmuel holds like רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda or not.